<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lord Generals letter in answer to the message of the Kentish-men, May 31. 1648. The Lord Generals proclamation against plundring, or taking any horses or goods from any of the inhabitants in Kent, and for restoring what hath been taken. Also a perfect relation of relieving Dover Castle, driving the Kentish-men to Rochester, the taking of the bidge [sic] near Norflet in Kent, the number killed and taken prisoners. With the names of the chief actors in this Kentish engagement. June 1. 1648. Imprimatur Gilbert Mabbot.</title>
            <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E445_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862503</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862503</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84786)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E445[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lord Generals letter in answer to the message of the Kentish-men, May 31. 1648. The Lord Generals proclamation against plundring, or taking any horses or goods from any of the inhabitants in Kent, and for restoring what hath been taken. Also a perfect relation of relieving Dover Castle, driving the Kentish-men to Rochester, the taking of the bidge [sic] near Norflet in Kent, the number killed and taken prisoners. With the names of the chief actors in this Kentish engagement. June 1. 1648. Imprimatur Gilbert Mabbot.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Laurence Chapman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>June 2. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Lord General = Thomas Fairfax, who signs A2r.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Kent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kent (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161757:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Lord Generals LETTER In Anſwer to the MESSAGE of the Kentiſh-men, MAY 31. 1648.</p>
            <p>The Lord Generals PROCLAMATION againſt Plundring, or taking any Horſes or Goods from any of the Inhabitants in <hi>Kent,</hi> and for reſtoring what hath been taken.</p>
            <p>Alſo a perfect Relation of Relieving Dover Caſtle, driving the Kentiſh-men to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> the taking of the Bidge near <hi>Norflet</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> the number kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and taken Priſoners.</p>
            <p>With the Names of the chief Actors in this Kentiſh Engagement.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>June 1. 1648.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Imprimatur</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Gilbert Mabbot.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>London, Printed for <hi>Laurence Chapman,</hi> June 2. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:161757:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161757:2"/>
            <head>For Sir <hi>Thomas Peyton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received by a Trumpet a Meſſage from you, whereby a Paſs was deſired for ſome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to come to me as Commiſſioners from your ſelf or others, to Treat, according to an Order of Parliament; To which, not knowing of any ſuch Order of Parliament to me, nor any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from Parliament to you or the reſt with you, to appoint Commiſſioners for ſuch a purpoſe, I could not make any Anſwer to any ſuch Overture: But, it hath given me occaſion to ſend this Bearer herewith unto you, deſiring you to ſignifie thus much to thoſe Gentlemen and others your countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with you, That whereas I finde them gathered together in Arms, and perſiſting therein without and againſt the Authority of Parliament, and doing many acts of Hoſtility, to the great damage of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors in this County, and diſturbance of the Peace thereof; I cannot admit of Treaty or capitulation with them, while ſo perſiſting in their Arms and Hoſtility, nor loſe time in proſecution of them. But if they ſhall forthwith lay down their Arms, and diſperſe themſelves to their ſeveral homes, I do not doubt but the mercy of the Parliament will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the eſtates and lives of thoſe many, who amongſt them ſhall appear to have been abuſed and deluded into this Rebellion; and their Juſtice againſt ſuch onely as ſhall appear to have been the chief and moſt eminent Actors and Fomentors thereof, and that chiefly for example to others, and neceſſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Damages already done.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Black-Heath, <date>30 Maii, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>THO: FAIRFAX.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="formal_order_against_plundering">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:161757:3"/>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION AGAINST <hi>PL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDRING.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas I have had ſeveral-Complaints, That divers Soldiers going into ſeveral mens houſes, under pretence of getting victuals and drink, have ſearched the rooms in their houſes, and have taken cloaths, linen and other goods: For the prevention of the like evil for the future, I do hereby ſtrictly require all Soldiers whatſoever under my command, That at their peril they do from henceforth forbear the like violences to the houſes or goods of any. And all Officers, as they will anſwer the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect at their perils, are ſtrictly to look to thoſe under their respective charges, to ſee that no ſuch things be done, or if they be, that the offenders be brought to puniſhment: Which I do hereby declare ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely executed And for the ſupplying of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with victuals and neceſſaries (while the Army ſhall keep the field, care ſhall be taken for bringing in and diſtributing the ſame in a publique way, or (if that fail, the Commanders of the respective Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Troops or companies, are to take care, That where there is a neceſsity of taking victuals for the Soldiers relief, ſome Officers to ſee it done orderly,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161757:3"/>and without further damage or prejudice to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants. And what ever ſuch goods hath been inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly taken from any as aforeſaid, I require that reſtitution be forthwith made, otherwiſe the perſons with whom ſuch goods ſhall be found, or thoſe by whom they were taken ſhall be immediately proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt according to Martial Law. And whereas I have likewiſe had ſeveral Complaints, That divers Horſes have been taken away by Soldiers out of mens houſes or grounds, under pretence that the owners have gone or ſent to the aſsiſtance of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in theſe parts, although the owners be not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in arms; I do hereby ſtrictly require, That all Horſes ſo taken, be forthwith restored, and that none under my command do from henceforth preſume to take any Horſes in ſuch maner from any countrey man, except ſuch as are and ſhall (at the ſame time) continue actually ingaged with the Rebels, nor from ſuch without Order from a Field Officer, or ſuperior Order, and that onely for the Publique uſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under my Hand and Seal <date>the One and thirtieth day of May, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>THO: FAIRFAX.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:161757:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Gave you an Accompt of the marches and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of that part of the Army under his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> now in <hi>Kent,</hi> on Monday and Tueſday laſt, I ſhall now preſent you with a continuation of the ſame.</p>
            <p>On Wedneſday <hi>May</hi> 31. His Excellency with four Regiments of Horſe and three of Foot, with ſome looſe Companies of Col: <hi>Ingoldsby</hi>'s Regiment, marched from Eitham (where they lay in the fields thereabouts the night before) to Craford Heath, where the ſaid Forces were drawn up to a Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz, and after that marched through Dartford, and then drew up on an Heath two miles from that Town, where his Excellency had Intelligence, That a party of the Kentiſh Rebels (not <hi>Browns</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels) had fortified and barricadoed a Bridge which led towards Graveſend; a commanded party was ſent forth under the conduct of Major <hi>Husbands,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Evanſons</hi> Troop, in all about 300 horſe, who mounted about an hundred foot behinde them: when they drew towards the Bridge, the enemy fired thick upon them; our men notwithſtanding fell on, and the horſe ſwam through the water, and ſo got over; by this time the enemy perceiving in what danger they were, fled: Major <hi>Childe</hi> who commanded them and was very active, hardly eſcaped, having his Horſe ſhot, whereupon he forſook it; his Son was ſhot in the back, and taken. There were about twenty ſlain in the place, divers wounded, and thirty Priſoners ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, many eſcaped, byhiding themſelves in the Corn fields and houſes. The enemies party conſiſted of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161757:4"/>Countrey-men thereabouts, the Seamen, and ſome London Apprentices: One Mr. <hi>Phips</hi> was very active in ſetting on the Countreymen.</p>
            <p>When we came to Norflet, half a mile beyond the Bridge, we underſtood the enemy were gone thence this morning by five of the clock, and not three men to be ſeen in the whole Town; their wives and friends left behinde, pretend they were forc'd out. One of our men in his paſſage over the River, had his horſe kild by falling upon an Harrow, which the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had laid in the water, ſo that his very guts came out (I went out with this party, and ſaw the whole buſines.)</p>
            <p>After this Major <hi>Husband</hi> advanced with a party two or three miles beyond Graveſend, and had after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Orders to march to Maulin, towards which the Army marches this morning from Mapham, a very ſmall village (where the Lord General quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed laſt night, and his Forces about it in the field) and will make an Hall near Maulin, where Orders will be given out. At the ending of this ſervice, Capt. <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and Capt. <hi>Barringtons</hi> Troops of Dragoons, who were ordered out of Wiltſhire, came up, and joyned with that party that lay towards Rocheſter, where the enemies greateſt body now is. His Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency hath ſent forth a Proclamation for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diſorders in Soldiers, a copy of which I have ſent you incloſed; as alſo of the Letter ſent from his Excellency to Sir <hi>Tho: Peyton,</hi> in anſwer to the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſent by Capt: <hi>Hackers</hi> Trumpeter to him. There are very few men to be ſeen in the Towns through which we march, but onely the women making ſad moan, fearing the ill ſucceſs their husbands are like
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161757:5"/>to have. The one my are very numerous, given out to be ten thouſand at leaſt, amongſt which a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Cavaliers. Their principal Ringleaders are, Sir <hi>Gamaliel Dudley,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Tracy,</hi> Col: <hi>Leigh,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Many,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho: Peyton,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho: Palmer,</hi> Squire <hi>Hales</hi> reported to be General, Sir <hi>Iames Hales,</hi> Sir <hi>William Many,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Dorrel,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho: Godfrey,</hi> Sir <hi>Richad Hardreſs,</hi> Col: <hi>Waſhington,</hi> Col: <hi>Hamond,</hi> Col: <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> Col: <hi>Culpepper,</hi> Col: <hi>Hacker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Iames Dorrel,</hi> Mr. <hi>George Newman,</hi> once a Colonel for the Parliament, and Mr. <hi>Whelton</hi> Treaſurer for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Sir <hi>Michael Liveſay</hi> ſent word laſt night, That he had recruited his Troop, and that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey came apace to the Deputy Lieu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enants; they deſired to have Orders from His Excellency, and accordingly had to joyn with the Army. I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgot one paſſage, Some of our Scouts meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this day with a party of theirs near <hi>Cobham,</hi> being askt <hi>Who they were for,</hi> made anſwer, <hi>For the Devil and King Charls:</hi> Our men replied, That they had taken King <hi>Charls,</hi> and hoped ere long to take the Devil too. Our men took yeſterday two Black coats Priſoners, amongſt others, the one of their names is <hi>Heydon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Major <hi>Gibbons</hi> hath raiſed the enemies ſiege before Dover-Caſtle, diſperſed them, and cleared the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between Dover and Sittinburn. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Mapham, <date>1 June, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
